A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Grants O-R FA732F
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Grants O-R
1936-2006
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA732F
33.6 Cubic Feet 3085 16mm microfilm reels, 275 35mm microfilm reels
Arrangement note
Each Ford Foundation Grant and the corresponding Grant File is identified by a unique Program Action (PA) number. PA numbers begin with the year a grant was made (2-digits), followed by a sequential number within that year (4-digits).
For example: PA 55-0123 was the 123rd grant made in the year 1955. PA numbers are often typed or handwritten on Ford documents in the following format: 55-123 (year)-(####). However, the Ford Foundation's grants database (LINKS) uses an 8-digit format for PA numbers: 05500123 (0YY#####).
Beginning in the 1970s the 4th digit in the 8-digit PA number was used to encode at least three different types of Ford grants:
0YY5#### = Delegated Authority Grants (DAG) / Delegated Authority Projects (DAP)
0YY6#### = Grants to Individuals
0YY9#### = Foundation Administered Projects (FAP)
After the year 2000 a "1" is used as the first digit in the 8-digit PA number to signify the 21st century. For example the 123rd grant made in 2012 would be PA number 11200123.
Grant Files were not microfilmed in numerical order, and the Ford Foundation's LINKS database must be used to identify on which microfilm reel (or reels) any specific Grant File is housed.
Arrangement note
Each Ford Foundation Grant File is arranged into 4 sections:
Section 1. BASIC DOCUMENTS: Program Action Forms Accepted Proposals Tax Forms an d Certifications Docket Excerpts Request for Grant Action (RGA) Grant Notification Letter & Budget Terms of Grant Grant Acceptance Letter Supplementary Requests & Agreements Modification Requests & Agreements Section 2. PAYMENTS: Requests Letters Acknowledgments Section 3. REPORTS: Grant Status Report Forms Grantee Narrative and Financial Reports Section 4. CORRESPONDENCE: All other correspondence and material, in reverse chronological order
A possible 5th section, 'ATTACHMENTS', will contain copies of printed ephemera & clippings related to the grant. Grant Files may also be followed by a 'Grants Accounting File' which summarizes the grant.
Also, early Grant Files (roughly 1950-1970) often include a CROSS REFERENCE sheet listing other grants made in a related subject or Program Area, and a 'BIBLIOGRAPHY of GRANT-RELATED MATERIALS' at the beginning of the file.
Scope and Contents
Grant administration files.
Conditions Governing Access
Microfilm of grants inactive for more than 10 years are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
- Ford Foundation Grants - O to R, 1941-2010
  - Oak Ridge Associated Universities, Inc. (06700448), 1967 September 01-1968 September 01 (Reel R1123)
    Grant Purpose
    Analysis of the use of mathematical models to study natural systems
    Program Name
    Education and Public Policy
    Grant Amount
    $90,000.00; $90,000.00
    Program Officer
    Felling, William E.
  - Oak Ridge Associated Universities, Inc. (07200110), 1972 February 01-1974 April 30 (Reel R1752)
    Support for a program of technical assistance to southern users of the 1970 census
    National Affairs [NA]
    $76,600.00; $76,600.00
    Pendleton, William C.
    United States
  - Oak Ridge Associated Universities, Inc. (07850861), 1978 August 01-1978 October 31 (Reel R2208)
    Seminar of latin american and u.s. Energy analysts
    $11,500.00; $11,500.00
    Pulsipher, Allan G.
    Western Hemisphere
  - Oak Ridge Associated Universities, Inc. (08050466), 1980 May 06-1981 June 30 (Reel R2211)
    Planning and initiation of fund-raising activities for the institute for energy analysis
    $10,000.00; $10,000.00
    Lisniewski, Theresa H.
  - Oakland Development Foundation (07000522), 1970 August 01-1971 December 31 (Reel R1279)
    Study of the economic feasibility & potential use of a cultural center for the performing arts in the east bay area
    Special Programs
    $12,500.00; $12,500.00
  - Oakland Neighborhood Housing Services, Inc. (07300132), 1973 January 16-1979 December 30 (Reel R4629)
    Program to stimulate private mortgage lending for a declining urban neighborhood
    Urban Poverty Program [UP]
    $100,000.00; $100,000.00
    McDonald, Bernard
  - Oakland Neighborhood Housing Services, Inc. (07650051), 1975 November 01-1976 July 31 (Reel R1204)
    For support of a prototype exterior treatment program in the oakland nhs target area
    $2,800.00; $2,800.00
    Miller, Anita
  - Oakland Planning and Development Corporation (08300638), 1983 July 01-1987 June 30 (Reel R5573)
    Partial support to expand housing development activities, undertake commercial revitalization projects and generate income
    $176,350.00; $176,350.00
    Howard, Craig
    Pittsburgh (Pa.)
  - Oakland Planning and Development Corporation (08501031), 1987 April 03-1994 April 02 (Reel R7135)
    Support to establish loss reserve in connection with pri loan
    US & International Affairs Programs - Office Of Vice President [USIAP/OVP]
    $50,000.00; $50,000.00
    Arrick, Ellen
  - Oakland Symphony Orchestra Association (06600306), 1966 July 01-1976 June 30 (Reel R2960, Reel R4342)
    Development and consolidation of american symphony orchestras (general support)
    Office Of Vice President -Finance & Administration
    $1,350,000.00; $1,350,000.00
    Thompson, Marcia T.
  - Oakland Unified School District (07200042), 1971 September 01-1972 November 30 (Reel R1303, Reel R3034)
    Part. Supp. Of a program of comprehensive community involvement leading to a master plan for the future direction of school
    $127,066.00; $127,066.00
    Smith, Joshua L.
  - Oakland Unified School District (08251168), 1981 October 15-1983 October 14 (Reel R4498)
    City high school recognition program grant for castlemont high school for school improvement activities
    $20,000.00; $19,144.00
    Meade, Edward J.
  - Oakland Unified School District (08251170), 1982 October 15-1983 October 14 (Reel R4668)
    City high school recognition program grant for freemont high school for school improvement activities
    $20,000.00; $18,939.00
  - Oaxaca Community Foundation (09851589), 1998 July 01-1999 September 30 (Reel R8352)
    Support to strengthen philanthropic endeavor in southern mexico
    Mexico and Central America (Mexico City)
    Farias Campero, Pablo
    Mexico; Humanitarianism--Mexico
  - Oaxacan Community Technical Assistance (10051585), 2000 June 01-2002 December 15 (Reel R9009)
    To carry out an extensive review of nearly 20 years of work promoting community-based forestry enterprises within indigenous communities throughout the state of oaxaca
    $40,000.00; $40,000.00
    Barry, Deborah
    Mexico; Forests and forestry -- Mexico -- Oaxaca; Community forests -- Mexico -- Oaxaca; Indians of North America -- Mexico -- Oaxaca -- Employment
  - Obafemi Awolowo University (06900508), 1969 June 16-1974 June 30 (Reel R1296, Reel R3792)
    Strengthening of nigerian staff and training capacity at the university
    West Africa (Lagos)
    $250,000.00; $250,000.00
    Fox, Melvin J.
  - Obafemi Awolowo University (06900697), 1969 September 30-1970 September 29 (Reel R2795, Reel R2796, Reel R3250)
    Seminar on national unity, ethnic tensions and reconciliation
    $14,000.00; $14,000.00
    Ward, Haskell G.
  - Obafemi Awolowo University (07000159), 1970 March 02-1976 February 28 (Reel R3046, Reel R3047, Reel R3692, Reel R3880, Reel R3881, Reel R3994)
    Support for a vernacular and english language development program
    $470,000.00; $470,000.00
    Biggs, Tyler S.
  - Obafemi Awolowo University (07100462), 1971 August 09-1976 August 31 (Reel R1428, Reel R3762)
    Support for a postgraduate course in development planning and administration at the university's institute of administration
    $436,000.00; $436,000.00
    Fox, Melvin J.; Goodwillie, Susan R.
  - Obafemi Awolowo University (07300417), 1973 July 11-1977 June 30 (Reel R2113, Reel R3869)
    Support for management reorganization at the university
    $132,000.00; $126,128.09
    Harbison, Ralph W.; Horovitz, Richard A.
    Education, Higher -- Nigeria
  - Obafemi Awolowo University (07500331), 1975 May 06-1983 July 31 (Reel R5548)
    Support for the faculty of agriculture's postgraduate program
    $300,000.00; $300,000.00
    Duggan, William R.
  - Obafemi Awolowo University (07500530), 1975 July 01-1983 December 31 (Reel R3811, Reel R4236)
    Interrelations between trade, investments and government policies in nigeria with extensions to the proposed wacm
    European and International Affairs
    Bayard, Thomas O.
  - Obafemi Awolowo University (07950537), 1979 May 01-1980 April 30 (Reel R3072, Reel R3861)
    Evaluative phase of the yoruba primary project
    $8,350.00; $8,350.00
  - Obafemi Awolowo University (08150203), 1980 November 21-1983 November 20 (Reel R5054, Reel R5323)
    Research and training program in international relations
    $332,000.00; $332,000.00
    Joseph, Richard A.
    Africa, West
  - Obafemi Awolowo University (08250725), 1981 June 01-1983 September 30 (Reel R5069, Reel R5248, Reel R5457)
    Multidisciplinary on-farm project by drs. P. Aina and y. Fabiyi
    $37,800.00; $31,600.00
    Nigeria
  - Obafemi Awolowo University (08300689), 1983 October 13-1989 March 06 (Reel R5559)
    Support for research and training in international affairs
    $380,000.00; $380,000.00
    Kubisch, Anne C.
  - Obafemi Awolowo University (08350316), 1981 June 01-1981 June 30 (Reel R5069, Reel R5306, Reel R5457)
    To support world conference on "the orisa tradition"
    $5,000.00; $4,380.00
    Horovitz, Richard A.
  - Obafemi Awolowo University (08351095), 1983 September 29-1986 May 31 (Reel R5763, Reel R5805)
    Nigerian component for international street foods project: survey of female vendors in ife (nigeria)
    $29,000.00; $27,469.40
    McLean, Mora L.
  - Obafemi Awolowo University (08450444), 1984 April 07-1985 April 06 (Reel R5531)
    Partial support for a national conference on inequality amd social policy (nigeria)
    $24,120.00; $24,120.00
  - Obafemi Awolowo University (08600671), 1986 September 01-1994 April 30 (Reel R6455, Reel R6568)
    Support for research and development of training course on management aspects of irrigation and river basin development in nigeria
    $175,000.00; $175,000.00
    Hicks, Frank
  - Obafemi Awolowo University (08600844), 1987 May 15-1992 June 30 (Reel R6455, Reel R6597)
    Study of the health and sanitation beliefs and behaviors of market vendors, and development of a model training course for them
    $65,500.00; $63,509.97
    Kanem, Natalia
  - Obafemi Awolowo University (08650767), 1986 July 18-1990 July 14 (Reel R5755, Reel R5881)
    Support for a seminar on the quality of life in nigeria
    $20,000.00; $20,000.00
  - Obafemi Awolowo University (08650810), 1986 September 29-1988 September 29 (Reel R5727, Reel R5728, Reel R5755)
    Support for the development of workshops for educators on population issues and adolescent sexuality (nigeria)
    $24,500.00; $22,193.23
    Jones, Nicola K. M.
  - Obafemi Awolowo University (08650815), 1987 May 26-1990 March 31 (Reel R5726, Reel R5755)
    Support for research on women's educational and employment status and fertility in southwestern nigeria
    $42,800.00; $42,800.00
  - Obafemi Awolowo University (08801129), 1988 December 09-1992 March 31 (Reel R6421, Reel R6453)
    Support for research and outreach activities on adolescent fertility among nigerian secondary school students
    $81,150.00; $81,096.73
  - Obafemi Awolowo University (08851035), 1988 August 12-1991 October 20 (Reel R5755, Reel R5900)
    Research on the effectiveness of four types of local institutions in nigeria
    $49,774.00; $49,774.00
    McLean, Mora L.; Hodges, Anthony D. C.
  - Obafemi Awolowo University (08851059), 1988 August 21-1990 December 31 (Reel R5755, Reel R5885)
    Support for a pilot appropriate technology program on food production and utilization for women
    $50,000.00; $38,513.51
  - Obafemi Awolowo University (08901304), 1989 November 02-1992 April 30 (Reel R6058)
    Support for a research and curriculum development program for local government health services
    $70,000.00; $69,402.72
  - Obafemi Awolowo University (09101212), 1991 November 01-1996 June 30 (Reel R8245)
    Support for research, training and exchange visits on local governance
    $300,000.00; $299,627.52
    Aidoo, Akwasi
  - Obafemi Awolowo University (10050537), 2000 January 01-2002 July 31 (Reel R8983)
    Support for re-establishing an outreach program for the university's department of theatre arts
    $67,850.00; $67,850.00
    Opoku-Mensah, Aida
    Nigeria; Arts -- Nigeria; Theater--Nigeria
  - Oberlin College (05600770), 1956 June 29-1966 June 28 (Reel R0324)
    To raise teachers@ salaries in private liberal arts and science colleges & universities in usa & terr. %endow. General support
    $918,000.00; $918,000.00
  - Oberlin College (05601068), 1956 June 29-1957 June 28 (Reel R0337)
    General support to advance academic program of private liberal arts & science colleges & universities in usa %accomplishment
    $569,500.00; $569,500.00
  - Oberlin College (05900030), 1958 November 21-1961 November 20 (Reel R0199)
    Conservatory of music salsburg program
    Office Of The Arts
    $47,500.00; $47,500.00
  - Oberlin College (05900304), 1959 June 17-1960 October 16 (Reel R0203)
    Use of teaching machines in a system of independent study
    $24,000.00; $24,000.00
  - Oberlin College (05900377), 1959 July 08-1964 July 07 (Reel R2526)
    Research in public affairs, governmental and political processes and public policies
    Watts, William
  - Oberlin College (06000187), 1960 March 25-1968 June 30 (Reel R2930)
    Strengthen teacher education
    $190,000.00; $190,000.00
    Fantini, Mario D.
  - Oberlin College (06300371), 1963 June 25-1966 June 24 (Reel R0986, Reel R0987)
    General support
    $2,200,000.00; $2,200,000.00
    Oleon, Sally J.
  - Oberlin College (06500243), 1965 June 03-1967 June 02 (Reel R1614)
    Prepare catalogue of european and american painting and sculpture collection in the allen memorial art museum
    $11,950.00; $11,950.00
    United States; Europe
  - Oberlin College (06800435), 1968 June 01-1972 May 31 (Reel R1897)
    Program of grants-in-aid at selected colleges for support of faculty development in the humanities
    Sheldon, Richard C.
  - Oberlin College (06900213), 1969 July 01-1970 June 30 (Reel R1630)
    Partial support for special services for enrolled negro students
    $28,125.00; $28,125.00
    Crossland, Fred E. (Fred Eugene)
  - Oberlin College (09701497), 1997 September 01-1999 July 31 (Reel R7949)
    Support for "crossing borders: revitalizing area studies"
    Education, Sexuality, Religion
    Volkman, Toby Alice
    United States; Global
  - Obninisk Municipal Informatics (10150216), 2000 November 01-2001 October 31 (Reel R8832)
    Support to enhance opportunities for Russian citizens to access municipal budget information and to participate in budget processes through innovative uses of information technology
    Russia (Moscow)
    $56,000.00; $52,989.00
    Kedzie, Christopher R.
    Russia; Municipal government--Russia (Federation)--Citizen participation; Municipal Budgets--Russia (Federation)
  - Obor, Inc. (07300188), 1973 February 01-1978 June 30 (Reel R4097, Reel R4586)
    Assistance to social science publishing in indonesia
    Indonesia (Jakarta)
    $92,000.00; $92,000.00
    Kessinger, Tom G.
    Indonesia
  - Obor, Inc. (08050294), 1979 November 01-1980 January 31 (Reel R2987)
    Support regional meeting in singapore about expansion of obor's activities in south and southeast asia
    Thailand
    $2,750.00; $2,595.64
    Weldon, Peter D.
    South Asia; SouthEast Asia
  - Observer Research Foundation (ORF) (10251461), 2002 November 22-2005 November 21 (Reel R9279)
    To establish the Center of Nepal Studies
    India, Nepal and Sri Lanka (New Delhi)
    $150,000.00; $150,000.00
    Rizvi, S. A. Gowher
    India; Nepal
  - Occidental College (05600376), 1956 June 29-1966 June 28 (Reel R0300)
    $394,000.00; $394,000.00
  - Occidental College (05600977), 1956 June 29-1957 June 28 (Reel R0336)
    $244,500.00; $244,500.00
  - Occidental College (06200349), 1962 June 22-1965 June 21 (Reel R0977)
    $2,500,000.00; $2,500,000.00
  - Occidental College (06500105), 1965 January 29-1969 July 31 (Reel R1621)
    Program to improve faculty competence in non-western areas
    $114,000.00; $114,000.00
    Barber, Elinor G.
    Global
  - Occidental College (06800436), 1968 June 01-1972 May 31 (Reel R1897)
  - Occidental College (08701042), 1987 September 01-1991 May 31 (Reel R6206)
    To improve the quality of undergraduate education & recruit future faculty/junior- and senior-year mentorship program
    Education & Culture Program [EC]
    Biddle, Sheila; Stanley, Peter W.
  - Occidental College (09100750), 1991 July 01-1998 June 30 (Reel R7474)
    To encourage undergeraduates to pursue careers as professors
    $200,000.00; $200,000.00
    Beckham, Edgar F.
  - Occidental College (09800476), 1997 November 01-1998 July 31 (Reel R7959)
    Research project to develop and analyze proposals for a housing tax credit to expand home ownership
    Economic Development
    $72,061.00; $72,061.00
    DeGiovanni, Frank F.
    United States; Home ownership -- United States; Tax Credits--United States; Minorities--Housing--Finance
  - Occidental College (10252019), 2002 September 02-2003 September 01 (Reel R8964)
    For the Urban & Environmental Policy Institute to organize ArroyoFest, a freeway walk & bike-ride event to promote community-building initiatives in transportation, the environment & cultural change
    Community and Resource Development
    Anthony, Carl
    California
  - Occupational Safety and Health Law Center (08550924), 1985 July 01-1989 April 30 (Reel R5694)
    Support for research, technical assistance and publications concerning mine safety in south africa
    Developing Country Programs [DCP]
    $99,296.00; $99,296.00
    Brown, Alice L.
    South Africa
  - Occupational Safety and Health Law Center (08950272), 1988 September 01-1994 April 30 (Reel R6568)
    Partial support for preparation of an organizational handbook for community-based public interest groups
    Rural Poverty & Resources Program [RPR]
    Campbell, Elizabeth C.
  - Ocean University of China (10350686), 2003 April 01-2004 October 31 (Reel R9246)
    For training and experimentation on village community governance and institutional development
    China (Beijing)
    Cook, Sarah
    China
  - Odhikar (09650607), 1995 October 01-1998 July 31 (Reel R8792)
    For an innovative bangladeshi human rights org. & for technical assistance provided by two distinguished off-shore institutions
    Bangladesh [ASIA/BA]
    $59,000.00; $59,000.00
    Lawry, Steven W.
    Bangladesh
  - Odn Productions, Inc. (08550731), 1985 June 01-1986 May 30 (Reel R5162)
    Free-loan distribution of adolescent pregnancy film, "in due time" to community groups and agencies
    $35,500.00; $35,500.00
    Arnold, David D.; Miller, Shelby H.
  - Odn Productions, Inc. (09201256), 1992 September 01-1994 February 28 (Reel R6659)
    Support for a multimedia educational program aimed at young people to prevent violence against women (008)
    Rights And Social Justice Program [RSJ]; US & International Affairs Programs - Office Of Vice President [USIAP/OVP]
    Neuborne, Helen; Taylor, Andrea L.
  - Off Off Broadway Alliance, Inc. (07800913), 1978 July 01-1982 June 30 (Reel R3373)
    Partial support of activities to strengthen off off broadway theatres
    $140,000.00; $140,000.00
    New York (State)
  - Off Off Broadway Alliance, Inc. (07850134), 1977 July 01-1978 June 30 (Reel R1331)
    Partial support of activities to strengthen off off broadway theaters
    Counts, Gayle M.
  - Office for Farmworker Ministry (08750669), 1987 May 01-1988 December 31 (Reel R5798, Reel R6259)
    Support for research to determine market interventions to enhance the welfare of florida farmworkers
    $45,100.00; $45,100.00
    Warner, Mildred E.
    Florida
  - Office for Farmworker Ministry (09000201), 1989 November 01-1994 March 31 (Reel R7431)
    Support for strengthening a labor contracting cooperative in central florida
  - Office For Law-Related Research (07300126), 1973 February 09-1976 February 08 (Reel R1089)
    $175,000.00; $.00
    Roditti, Esther C.
  - Office for Legal Aid and Orientation (09000817), 1990 April 01-1993 April 01 (Reel R6408, Reel R6451)
    Support for legal education, technical assistance, training, research, & national meeting of legal services organizations in mexico
    Krasevac, Kimberly A.; Lopez, Jose Gabriel
    Mexico
  - Office for the Defense of the Rights of Women (DEMUS) (08900813), 1989 August 01-1995 June 30 (Reel R7005, Reel R7488)
    Support for a program in support of women's rights
    Andean Region & Southern Cone-Peru; Andean Region and Southern Cone (Santiago)
    $230,000.00; $230,000.00
    Wilde, Alexander; Varas, Augusto
    Peru; Rape--Prevention--Peru; Sex crimes--Peru
  - Office for the Defense of the Rights of Women (DEMUS) (09150776), 1991 April 01-1994 July 31 (Reel R7062)
    Support to a women's police station concerned with domestic violence
    Andean Region and Southern Cone (Santiago)
    $45,000.00; $45,000.00
    Peru
  - Office for the Defense of the Rights of Women (DEMUS) (09550582), 1995 June 01-1996 June 30 (Reel R6688, Reel R7463)
    Support for analysis, workshops and promotion of legal reform against sexual violence
    $66,000.00; $66,000.00
    Shepard, Bonnie L.; Varas, Augusto
  - Office for the Defense of the Rights of Women (DEMUS) (10001535), 2000 August 01-2004 December 31 (Reel R9274)
    Creation of an NGO's Fund to support grassroots organizations working on women's human rights, reproductive rights and gender equity issues in Peru
    $620,000.00; $620,000.00
    Abreg, Martn; Ore Aguilar, Gaby; Varas, Augusto
    Peru; Human rights -- Peru; Women's rights--Peru
  - Office for the Yunnan Provincial Leading Group for the Economic Development of Poor Areas (09000256), 1990 January 01-1999 February 28 (Reel R8109)
    Support for research, training and experimentation on upland development in yunnan province
    $1,330,000.00; $1,330,000.00
    Mallee, Henricus P.; Harkness, James S.
  - Office for the Yunnan Provincial Leading Group for the Economic Development of Poor Areas (09900303), 1999 January 01-2001 December 31 (Reel R8199)
    Support for a workshop on upland development in yunnan province
    $67,548.00; $67,548.00
    Mallee, Henricus P.
    China; Upland conservation--China; Conservation of natural resources -- China
  - Office of Communication of the United Church of Christ (10000210), 1999 November 01-2001 October 31 (Reel R8795)
    Support to organize communities of color to support creation of a low power radio service and to equip these communities with the organizational and technical skills to establish such stations
    Media Arts and Culture
    Lentz, Roberta G.; Santos, John Phillip
    United States; Radio Broadcasting policy--United States
  - Office of Communication of the United Church of Christ (10350845), 2003 April 01-2004 September 30 (Reel R9138)
    Start-up support for the Media Empowerment Project, a grassroots initiative to add an organizing arm to the office's ongoing legal work on behalf of the public interest in communications policy
    Lentz, Roberta G.
  - Office of Economic Development of Poor Areas in Sichuan (09550667), 1995 April 01-1996 December 31 (Reel R8071)